When we think about mapping cities,
عندما نفكر في رسم خريطة للمدن،
we tend to think about roads and streets and buildings,
نميل إلى التفكير في الطرق والشوارع والمباني
and the settlement narrative that led to their creation,
وحكاية السكن التي أدّت إلى بنائها،
or you might think about the bold vision of an urban designer,
أو ربما تفكر في بُعد نظر لمُصمِّم حضريّ،
but there's other ways to think about mapping cities
ولكن هناك طرق أخرى للتفكيرعن رسم المدن
and how they got to be made.
والوسيلة التي يتم بنائها بها.
Today, I want to show you a new kind of map.
في هذا اليوم، أريد أن أريكم نوعاً جديداً من الخرائط.
This is not a geographic map.
هذه ليست خريطة جغرافية.
This is a map of the relationships between people in my hometown
هذه خريطة العلاقات بين الناس في مسقط رأسي،
of Baltimore, Maryland,
بالتيمور، ماريلاند،
and what you can see here is that each dot represents a person,
وما تستطيعون رؤيته هنا هو أن كلَّ نقطةٍ تمثل شخصاً
each line represents a relationship between those people,
وكلَّ سطرٍ يمثل علاقة بين هؤلاء الأشخاص
and each color represents a community within the network.
وكلَّ لونٍ يمثل مجتمعاً داخل إطار الشبكة.
Now, I'm here on the green side, down on the far right where the geeks are,
الآن، أنا هنا على الجانب الأخضر، بالأسفل على أقصى اليمين حيث يتواجد المهووسون
and TEDx also is down on the far right. (Laughter)
و TEDx أيضاً في الأسفل على أقصى اليمين. (َضحك)
Now, on the other side of the network,
الآن، على الجانب الآخر من الشبكة،
you tend to have primarily African-American and Latino folks
تميل بشكل رئيس إلى رؤية أناس من الأمريكيين الأفارقة واللاتينيين
who are really concerned about somewhat different things than the geeks are,
القلقين حقاً بشان أشياء مختلفة عن تلك التي يقلق بشأنها المهووسون،
but just to give some sense,
ولكن حتى أعطيكم فكرة عن الأمر،
the green part of the network we call Smalltimore,
نسمي الجزء الأخضر من الشبكة سمولتيمور،
for those of us that inhabit it,
بالنسبة للذين يقطنونها منا،
because it seems as though we're living in a very small town.
لأنه يبدو وكأننا نعيش في بلدة صغيرة جداً.
We see the same people over and over again,
نرى نفس الأشخاص مراراً وتكراراً،
but that's because we're not really exploring
ولكنّ ذلك بسبب أننا لا نكتشف حقاً
the full depth and breadth of the city.
العمق والعرض الكامل للمدينة.
On the other end of the network,
في الطرف الآخر من الشبكة،
you have folks who are interested in things like hip-hop music
تجد أناساً يهتمون بأشياء مثل موسيقى الهيب هوب
and they even identify with living in the DC/Maryland/Virginia area
وحتى أنهم يُعرفون بالعيش في منطقة نيويورك/ميريلاند/فيرجينيا
over, say, the Baltimore city designation proper.
فلنقل عند مدينة بالتيمور، الاسم الصحيح لها.
But in the middle, you see that there's
ولكنك ترى في الوسط بأن هناك
something that connects the two communities together,
شيئاً ما يربط هذين المجتمعين معاً
and that's sports.
وهو الرياضة.
We have the Baltimore Orioles, the Baltimore Ravens football team,
لدينا فريق بالتيمور أويلوس وفريق بالتيمور ريفنز لكرة القدم
Michael Phelps, the Olympian.
وفريق مايكل فيليبس والأولومبيان.
Under Armour, you may have heard of, is a Baltimore company,
أندر آرمور، ربما سمعتم بها، شركة في بالتيمور،
and that community of sports acts as the only bridge
ومجتمع الرياضات ذاك يتصرفون كالجسر الوحيد
between these two ends of the network.
بين هذين الطرفين من الشبكة.
Let's take a look at San Francisco.
دعونا نلقي نظرة على سان فرانسيسكو.
You see something a little bit different happening in San Francisco.
ترون شيئاً مختلفاً يحدث في سان فرانسيسكو.
On the one hand, you do have the media, politics and news lobe
من ناحية، تجدون الإعلام والسياسة والأقسام الإخبارية
that tends to exist in Baltimore and other cities,
التي تميل إلى التواجد في بالتيمور وغيرها من المدن،
but you also have this very predominant group
ولكن أيضاً تجدون هذه المجموعة ذات النسبة غير البسيطة
of geeks and techies that are sort of taking over the top half of the network,
من المهووسين والفنيين الذين نوعاً ما يسيطرون على النصف الأعلى من الشبكة،
and there's even a group that's so distinct and clear
حتى أن هناك مجموعة مميزة وواضحة جداً
that we can identify it as Twitter employees,
بإمكاننا تعريفها كموظفي تويتر،
next to the geeks, in between the gamers and the geeks,
إلى جانب المهووسين، بين اللاعبين والمهووسين،
at the opposite end of the hip-hop spectrum.
في الطرف المقابل لطيف الهيب هوب.
So you can see, though,
إذن فبإمكانكم أن تروا، مع ذلك،
that the tensions that we've heard about in San Francisco
أن التوترات التي قد سمعنا عنها في سان فرانسيسكو،
in terms of people being concerned about gentrification
من ناحية أن الأشخاص قلقين بشأن الاستطباق
and all the new tech companies that are bringing new wealth
وكل شركات التقنية الجديدة التي تحضر ثروةً جديدةً
and settlement into the city are real,
وسكناً إلى المدينة، هي توترات حقيقية،
and you can actually see that documented here.
وبإمكانكم بالفعل أن تشاهدوها موثقة هنا.
You can see the LGBT community
بإمكانكم أن تشاهدوا أن مجتمع المثليين والمتحولين جنسياً
the arts community, the music community.
أو مع مجتمع الفنون ومجتمع الموسيقى.
And so it leads to things like this.
ولذا فإن ذلك يقود إلى أشياء كهذه.
["Evict Twitter"]
["قم بطرد تويتر"]
Somebody sent me this photo a few weeks ago,
أرسل لي أحدهم هذه الصورة قبل بضعة أسابيع،
and it shows what is happening on the ground in San Francisco,
وهي تظهر ما يحدث الآن على الأرض في سان فرانسيسكو،
and I think you can actually try to understand that
وأعتقد أن بإمكانكم في الحقيقة أن تحاولوا فهم ذلك
through looking at a map like this.
من خلال النظر إلى خريطة كهذه.
Let's take a look at Rio de Janeiro.
دعونا نلقي نظرة على ريو دي جانيرو.
I spent the last few weeks gathering data about Rio,
أمضيت الأسابيع القليلة الماضية وأنا أجمع معلومات عن ريو،
and one of the things that stood out to me about this city
وأحد الأشياء التي اتضحت لي عن هذه المدينة
is that everything's really kind of mixed up.
أن كل شيء فيها في الحقيقة مختلط نوعاً ما.
It's a very heterogenous city in a way that Baltimore or San Francisco is not.
إنها مدينة متباينة جداً بطريقة تختلف عن بالتيمور أو سان فرانسيسكو.
You still have the lobe of people involved
لا زال بإمكانك أن تجد فريقاً من الناس يعملون في
with government, newspapers, politics, columnists.
الحكومة والصحف والسياسة والتحرير الصحفي.
TEDxRio is down in the lower right, right next to bloggers and writers.
يوجد TEDxRio في أسفل اليمين، مباشرةً إلى جانب الكتاب والمدونين.
But then you also have this tremendous diversity of people
ولكنك أيضاً تجد تنوعاً هائلاً من الأشخاص
that are interested in different kinds of music.
المهتمين بأنواع مختلفة من الموسيقى.
Even Justin Bieber fans are represented here.
حتى أن معجبي جستن بيبر تم تمثيلهم هنا.
Other boy bands, country singers,
وهناك فرق شابة أخرى ومغنيو كونتري
gospel music, funk and rap and stand-up comedy,
وموسيقى غوسبل وفنك وراب وستاند أب كوميدي،
and there's even a whole section around drugs and jokes.
وحتى أن هناك قسم كامل عن المخدرات والنكت.
How cool is that?
كم هذا رائع!
And then the Flamengo football team is also represented here.
ومن ثم فإن فريق فلامينغو لكرة القدم تم تمثيله هنا أيضاً.
So you have that same kind of spread
إذن تجدون نفس النوع من الانتشار
of sports and civics and the arts and music,
للرياضة والتربية المدنية والفنون والموسيقى
but it's represented in a very different way,
ولكنها ممثَّلة بطريقة مختلفة جداً،
and I think that maybe fits with our understanding of Rio
وأعتقد أن ذلك يتناسب مع فهمنا لمدينة ريو
as being a very multicultural, musically diverse city.
كونها مدينة متعددة الثقافات وذات تعددية موسيقية بشكل كبير.
So we have all this data.
إذن لدينا كل هذه البيانات.
It's an incredibly rich set of data that we have about cities now,
إنها مجموعة غنية بشكل مدهش بالبيانات التي نملكها عن المدن الآن،
maybe even richer than any data set that we've ever had before.
ربما أكثر غنىً من أي مجموعة بيانات قد سبق لنا وأن امتلكناها.
So what can we do with it?
إذن ما الذي نستطيع فعله بها؟
Well, I think the first thing that we can try to understand
حسناً، أعتقد أن أول شيء يمكننا أن نحاول فعله هو فهم
is that segregation is a social construct.
أن التمييز هو بناء إجتماعي.
It's something that we choose to do, and we could choose not to do it,
إنه شيء نختارُ فعله وبإمكاننا أن نختار عدم فعله،
and if you kind of think about it,
وإذا فكرتم في هذا الأمر بطريقة ما،
what we're doing with this data is aiming a space telescope at a city
فإن ما نفعله بهذه البيانات هو توجيهُ مقرابٍ فضائي نحو المدينة
and looking at it as if was a giant high school cafeteria,
والنظر إليها كما لو كانت كافيتريا لمدرسة ثانوية ضخمة،
and seeing how everybody arranged themselves in a seating chart.
ومشاهدة كيف قام الجميعُ بترتيب أنفسهم في شكل مخطط جلوس.
Well maybe it's time to shake up the seating chart a little bit.
حسناً، ربما هذا هو الوقت لإعادة تنظيم مخطط الجلوس قليلاً.
The other thing that we start to realize
الشيء الآخر الذي بدأنا ندركه
is that race is a really poor proxy for diversity.
هو أن العِرْق هو مؤشر ضعيف على التعددية.
We've got people represented from all different types of races
لدينا أشخاص مثَّلوا جميع الأعراق المختلفة
across the entire map here --
على امتداد الخريطة هنا بأكلمها --
only looking at race
إن النظر على العِرْق وحده
doesn't really contribute to our development of diversity.
لا يساهم بالفعل بتطوير التعددية خاصتنا.
So if we're trying to use diversity
لذا إن كنا نحاول استخدام التعددية
as a way to tackle some of our more intractable problems,
كطريقة لمعالجة بعض مشاكلنا الأكثر صعوبة،
we need to start to think about diversity in a new way.
فنحن نحتاج للبدء في التفكير بشأن التعددية بطريقة جديدة.
And lastly, we have the ability to create
وفي الختام، لدينا الإمكانية لصناعة
interventions to start to reshape our cities in a new way,
التدخلات للبدء في إعادة تشكيل مُدُننا بطريقة جديدة،
and I believe that if we have that capability,
وأنا أؤمن أننا إذا امتلكنا تلك المقدرة،
we may even bear some responsibility to do so.
ربما نتحمل بعض المسؤولية لفعل ذلك.
So what is a city?
إذن ما هي المدينة؟
I think some might say that it is
أعتقد أن البعض ربما يقولون أنها
a geographical area or a collection of streets and buildings,
منطقة جغرافية أو مجموعة من الشوارع والمباني،
but I believe that a city is the sum of the relationships
ولكنني أعتقد أن المدينة هي مجموع علاقات
of the people that live there,
الأشخاص الذين يعيشون هناك،
and I believe that if we can start to document those relationships in a real way
وأعتقد أننا إن استطعنا البدء في توثيق هذه العلاقات بطريقة حقيقية،
then maybe we have a real shot
عندها لربما نمتلك الفرصة الحقيقية
at creating those kinds of cities that we'd like to have.
لبناء هذه الأنواع من المدن التي نود امتلاكها.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)